[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the ask Abhijit Show
episode 153 I hope you're all doing very
well and thank you for being on this
live stream with me this fine evening
over here
so as always before we dive into the
questions let's take a look at who all
is there on the live chat I can see on
human K10 Kumar world leaders app
developer 5121 Sunday
foreign
strangely proton Deepak
America
foreign
I think I'm repeating some names now so
let me stop here so good evening good
day to all of you great to be amongst
you all for this live stream for the ask
committee show so with that done let us
dive into the questions now and let's
see what questions we have uh these days
you know I'm getting thousands of
questions every week every week it's
increasing the number of questions and
in every episode I can take about 20 25
30 questions and more so apologies in
advance to those of you whose questions
I am unable to take I can only take a
bunch so I I have decided that I'm gonna
take one question per person from now on
there are obviously some people who ask
lots of questions uh but I think just to
be fair to everybody I will take from
now onwards one question per person and
that way I can spread it out over as
many people as possible and obviously I
will take good questions not not
questions that have been repeated it and
I've been answered before sometimes I do
that because you know it's been a while
but yeah I will that's that's the gonna
be the policy going forward mostly one
question per person
so with that said let's get into the
questions what's question number one
it's by subho datta do you see a nuclear
war incoming is France and Poland are
trying to give Ukraine attacking fighter
jets and the U.S is trying to give
long-range ballistic missiles and Israel
is giving Iron Dome to Ukraine well you
know
a nuclear war is you know it's certainly
a big danger that's uh upon us there is
something called the Doomsday Clock
shall we take a look at the Doomsday
Clock let's Google it and find out
um let's go to Google I'll put that on
the on the screen the Doomsday Clock is
about how far we are from doomsday
essentially uh nuclear disaster so let's
see where the
Dooms they clock
but search for that this is it bulletin
of the atomic scientists it says that
it's a time of unprecedented danger it's
90 seconds to midnight
so it's essentially the closest we have
ever been most likely to nuclear war
that's what this Doomsday Clock says
and uh obviously you if you scroll down
you will find the details of what it's
all about it's all about blaming Russia
for what's happening and Russia is the
bad guy it's all thanks to Russia it's
always been that way yeah uh so
according to the Doomsday Clock we are
very close to nuclear war now uh
obviously we have had certain events
that have kind of
you know it it kind of pushes us towards
that situation for instance the
ukrainians a few couple of months ago
very recently they launched a missile at
Poland it it crashed into a village it
killed at least a couple of people and
then they blamed the Russians for doing
that they knew what was what it was it
was their missile they tried to blame
Russia for it and they were trying to
drag NATO into an open war with Russia
thus far as Ukraine conflict is a proxy
war Ukraine is a proxy of the US and
NATO
in by doing this the ukrainians were
trying to drag NATO into a direct
conflict they they wanted NATO to get
involved directly so that is something
that's a major escalation then that can
certainly lead to unforeseen
consequences including eventually
nuclear war you know there's a whole
escalation letter ladder that's about 20
30 steps long and we are kind of midway
between into that you know so yeah it's
it's dangerous times that we're living
in now uh France and Poland are giving
fighter jets yeah they're talking about
doing that uh
how many will they actually give and
even if you let's say the French give a
bunch of rafales let's say 10 rafales do
the Ukrainian fighter pilots know how to
fly the rafale takes several months to
train an already trained pilot on a new
aircraft
so it's you know all this is just stock
have has anybody actually sent uh these
fighter jets uh to Ukraine not not so
much right
um and maybe they could give uh
fightages that the ukrainians are
already used to Flying that's not
happened yet it's all words it's all
rhetoric it's all dark right now it's
not really happened if it happens even
if it happens like yesterday I was
speaking about tanks
um
the the uh it's it's a grand total of
less than 100 tanks that are going to
Ukraine and that too most of them are
like say 1960s tanks yeah so on the one
hand there's this grandiose and very
belligerent and belly Coast talk on the
other hand there is this token support
to Ukraine so um so let's see if they
actually send fighter planes and what
kind of fighter planes they send and how
many they send 20 fighter planes 3500
lens will not make much of a difference
right uh when it comes to long range
ballistic missiles you know ballistic
missiles are are kind of a red line you
can give uh short range missiles you
know long range missiles are a game
changer and that's a kind of causing a
line of no return yeah uh if you enable
Ukraine to start launching missiles at
Moscow that's gonna be a very major
escalation so I I've not heard of this
happening any of the Americans do it
it's going to be a very significant
escalation it's not happened thus far is
Royal when it comes to the Iron Dome
system the Iron Dome system is Israel's
anti-missile defense system which can
take out which can protect Israeli
territories from the kind of rockets
that Hezbollah launches at them and also
also I'm sure uh ballistic missiles scud
missiles like the like the Iraqis used
to have and so on yep uh
so the Israelis have spoken about
their thinking about the possibility
they're considering the possibility in
weighing the options of weather to give
the Iron Dome to Ukraine or not the
ukrainians had requested they had asked
they demanded for the Iron Dome system I
think last year
October September October 2022 if I'm
not mistaken and uh right now Mr
Netanyahu is the new is the prime
minister of Israel and he's saying that
he's considering this this request you
know he's thinking they will they will
consider this seriously so thus far it's
just talk nothing has actually happened
but if certain escalations happen you're
gonna have a response to those
escalations so in case the Americans
let's say give a bunch of f-16s to
Ukraine that can cause a change in the
balance of power and then you will see
certain actions that Russia will be made
to take in response to such a such an
action if the French for instance
hypothetically hypothetically send let's
say 10 rafales to uh Ukraine that's
going to be a major escalation and the
Russians will take certain actions and
that's how it is so yeah the more such
things happen the more there is the
chance of an escalation and escalations
can go out of control at times that's
what Warfare teaches us so yes we are
kind of in dangerous territory right now
I hope there's no nuclear war right now
it doesn't look like there's going to be
a nuclear war but there's been a lot of
talk about nukes and all that rhetoric
uh but one hopes that sane and cool
heads will prevail better sense will
prevail and uh
and there is no uh significant
escalation whatever what happens happens
in conventional in a conventional way
it's it's going on and it's it's by no
means settled the matter right now so
yeah so thus far things are okay but you
know if somebody takes a makes a stupid
choice and does something as collectory
and uh then that could cause problems
could lead us to nuclear war one hopes
that doesn't happen
if if if says there have been reports
that Russia is going to sell 24 Sukhoi
35 fighter jets to Iran how will Israel
in the new Netanyahu government which
has restrained from sending weapons to
Ukraine and is more neutral towards the
conflict how is this government going to
respond to this could Israel soon start
sending weapons to Ukraine good question
interesting question so yes it is indeed
the case that uh
that Russia is on the verge of sending a
bunch of Sukhoi 20 35 fighter jets to
Iran so I think the payment has already
been done by Iran and I think the
Iranians could start receiving these
Jets by March this year that's in a
month or two from now yes I'm not sure
if they'll get the entire batch of 24
Jets at once or whether this will start
trickling it
trickling in three four at a time or so
we don't quite know about that but yes
this deal is a done deal and the
Russians are on the verge of of sending
of starting to send these Sukhoi 35
fighter planes to Iran now Iran has very
ancient American-made fighter planes I'd
forget them
f-86 or something I don't remember which
one it was it's quite old yeah but if
they receive when they receive these
Sukho 35s it's gonna drastically uh
increase their War fighting and their
superiority capabilities the Sukhoi 35
is a hyper maneuverable 4.5 generation
fighter plane it is one of the best
fighter planes in the world it's not a
fifth generation fighter plane but it's
you could say it's kind of in the same
league as the rafale that India has
so the Sukhoi 35 is an extremely good
and capable 4.5 generation fighter plane
it's in some ways possibly better than
the Sukhoi 30s that India has so if Iran
receives 24 of these it's gonna totally
change their capabilities and uh it
could give them a significant advantage
over various adverse origin enemies it
could set off alarm bells in let's say
in Saudi Arabia in Israel of course and
uh in Pakistan I would assume and and so
on yeah
and it could also I mean if you if you
look at the map let's go to the map yes
where's the map we must see the map
which gives us a better understanding of
what's Happening
so look at the geography we know where
Iran is I'm sure we all do yes so Iran
occupies an interesting neighborhood uh
the Caspian Sea Coast is at the north of
Iran and so is the Caucasus region and
uh Ukraine isn't that far away neither
is Israel and these fighter planes there
is can certainly go to go and strike
Israel and come back to Iran certainly
within the capability of the fighter
plane so it's going to
change the balance of power
significantly in favor of Iran once this
happens so how will Israel respond to
this Israel obviously considers Iran a
mortal enemy because Iran has been
making these statements for the longest
time that they want to wipe Israel from
the map of of the earth of the planet
so it's going to set off alarm bells in
Israel now how will Israel deal with
this is the question if it starts arming
Ukraine it's not going to neutralize the
Iran threat will it it's not going to
neutralize the Iran threat and we have
to understand why Russia is doing this
Russia is obviously uh selling this this
weapon system to to Iran for certain
reasons see Russia needs the cooperation
of Iran in order to to link itself to
India via the international north south
transport Corridor the insdc
um this in STC is going to essentially
connect Mumbai and various Indian ports
via Bahar in Iran and also bandar Abbas
where is jabahar shabbahar is here as
you can see
here at the choke point the Strait of
Hormuz then the the uh the corridor will
go all the way into Azerbaijan Baku
through through and then into Russia
maybe it will bypass Georgia it's not
there's no need to go through Georgia so
for this to happen uh Russia Russia does
need Iran's cooperation Russia also
wants to as we discussed yesterday they
have linked all their banks with the
Iranian Banks so they have established
interconnectivity so there is this kind
of Alliance that's happening and Russia
is kind of isolated from a significant
uh so significant extent because of the
western U.S sanctions uh imposed on it
so Russia has been able to tie to to to
um tide over this crisis it's not
exactly tie a door but it's still
ongoing but they've been able to
withstand the bulk of this crisis
because of their relationship with Iran
with India and with China these are
three major Iran is a junior partner if
you would consider Russia and India and
China but these three nations are
essentially with with whom Iraq Russia
is carrying out the bulk of its trade
and various other activities
so Russia needs Iran on its side and uh
so India and Iran are also cooperating
in this matter and there obviously we
know about the fact that the Chinese
have invested in are in the process of
investing about 400 billion dollars
worth of money into Iran over the next
25 or so years that's that agreement
that they've had so Russia needs this
and that's why maybe the Iranians have
asked for this that you know if you want
our cooperation sell us these fighter
planes so the Russians have done this
obviously it's bad for Israel so the
question is what does Israel do about
this maybe they could carry out air
strikes on Iran that's a very drastic
thing to do they have done such things
in the past but uh uh when you have
Sukhoi 35s in the air it's not that easy
to take take those out especially when
the Israelis have the f-16s and whatever
else they have f-18s perhaps do they
have the f-35s yet I'm not sure if they
have it then it could be a more uh Pro
the the balance of the air battle good
turn in in favor of Israel but yes so
it's uh
it's a conundrum for Israel on the one
hand they could arm Ukraine but that
does not solve the problem when you have
such such an issue you have to solve the
problem instead of going somewhere else
so I'm not sure if Israel will take the
action will will choose to start sending
weapons to Ukraine and in even Israel
and Russia have some sort of
understanding when it comes to Ukraine
Israel is
restrained itself and it has not uh
agreed thus far to send anything
significant in terms of military aid to
Ukraine and most likely even if they do
send something it will not be anything
substantial that's how it looks now
let's see because starting to send
Weapons Systems and military aid to
Ukraine does not solve this problem of
the Iranian Sukhoi 35s so they will have
to find a solution to this if it is at
all possible but this is something
that's going to happen the Russians are
about to send a bunch of Sukhoi 35s to
Iran most likely starting in March in a
month from now the deliveries will most
likely start from March onwards so yeah
interesting and we're going to keep an
eye on this
says uh my question is
if the
um if there's a Fallout between turkey
and the rest of NATO what implications
will it have on Armenia and the other on
the Armenia Azerbaijan conflict good
question let's go to the map
where's the map here's the map
let's okay it doesn't all right so where
is Turkey Turkey is here now let's
understand
the actual the true significance the
true geopolitical geostrategic
significance and importance of turkey
from the eyes of NATO NATO means the U.S
NATO is just a euphemism for the U.S and
its satellite States so NATO so for the
US what is the importance geopolitical
and geostrategic importance of turkey so
let me explain what that is turkey if
you go to Istanbul
so let's zoom in to the agency you can
see there is this uh there is this place
called The Sea called the Sea of marmara
and this is an inland sea which is which
connects the agency which is a part of
the Mediterranean to the Black Sea
okay and there are two very significant
very important truth points here
the first is the darnells the Strait of
the Dardanelles where you had in 1960
1915 or so this terrible disaster uh the
British were defeated by the Turks by by
Mustafa Turk over here the Gallipoli
campaign so this is a very significant
and very important choke point which is
controlled by turkey and the other
choke point is this one here right the
Bosphorus Strait which passes through
Istanbul and connects the Sea of marmala
to the Black Sea
and the Black Sea is where the action is
you know the Crimea and the the coast of
Ukraine and obviously you have Russia as
well and the Caucasus region the Western
Caucasus region so these choke points
the Strait of Bosphorus in the Strait of
of the Dardanelles are extremely
important geopolitically because they
serve to if you control these states
these traits you essentially can choke
off any Russian attempt to move warships
into the Mediterranean Sea so that's why
it's extremely important you can you can
monitor all Russian activity Naval
activity and you can control it at will
if you control these joke points so
turkey controls the joke that's why the
for since since the longest time the
Western Nations have had this interest
in Turkey because of this this extremely
important position it straddles which is
which is the de facto so to say boundary
between Europe and Asia
so half of Istanbul half of
Constantinople is in Europe half as in
Asia that's how it is seen these are
artificial divisions so the real
importance of turkey is this and
obviously it's a major country and all
that
so now let's say so the Americans have
ensured that turkey becomes a part of
NATO this happened I think in 1950 if
I'm not mistaken turkey is one of the I
think founding members if I'm not
mistaken of NATO
and uh the U.S has a certain amount of
military presence in Turkey I believe
that the U.S even may have nuclear
weapons on Turkish territory
and turkey obviously has its own
Ambitions I spoke about that yesterday
uh Mr erdogan has his own Neo Imperial
Ambitions he wants to essentially
recreate he hopes to essentially
recreate the Ottoman Empire so turkey is
an expansionist uh Nation
and uh we know that it has it is in the
process it is currently occupying parts
of Syria uh and and it also occupies
Northern Cyrus Cyprus and all that so
turkey is very important and NATO or the
US cannot afford to let turkey slip away
from its grasp right it cannot afford to
have that happen because then the
Americans will lose uh control over
these extremely vital choke points
now let's say hypothetically turkey see
turkey has been doing things that the
Americans don't like for instance the
Turks uh who are part of the F-35
program they were supposed to receive
F-35 fighter jets
the Turks decided to acquire the s-400
anti-missile air defense system from the
Russians
they have already acquired it and
because of this the Americans canceled
the turkey's participation in the F-35
program so this is something that has
greatly displeased the US so turkey is
pursuing a semi-independent foreign
policy which is at times quite at odds
with the interests of NATO in the U.S
there are the other nation that you can
think of which pursues a
semi-independent foreign policy is
France but France is not that
confrontational with the US France tries
to uh keep a conciliatory approach even
though the Americans have at times uh
kind of you would say backstabbed France
like the the submarine Saga with the
Australians right
so let's say hypothetically the Turks uh
break out break off with with NATO and
and they let's say they
they remove themselves from from NATO or
whatever then what does what happens
then that would I would say lead to
the arrival of democracy and human
rights and freedom and peace in Turkey
which means a U.S military or operation
that's the only thing one can think of
see turkey doesn't have nuclear weapons
it has nuclear American nuclear weapons
on its soil which are under U.S control
so uh it doesn't have the the luxury of
having nuclear weapons it does have a
good military and all but it obviously
is no match
uh to the US military so what could the
U.S do in case turkey says I'm no longer
gonna you know bend it to your will the
Americans could uh
could instigate a Greece versus Turkey
War they could arm Greece substantially
they are in a position to do that they
could take sides in Cyprus and maybe
evict the Turks from Cyprus that's a
possibility they could uh see Romania
Bulgaria all of these nations uh kind of
are on the U.S side so is Greece Greece
and Turkey have a very old enmity so the
U.S could use all that very easily and
ferment trouble in turkey and maybe do a
regime change or or something along
those lines
and now about the Armenia Azerbaijan
concrete yes see uh turkey the U.S is is
okay with whatever the Turks are doing
in Armenia they essentially want to wipe
Armenia off the face of the Earth they
want to finish what they started and
could not finish in 1915.
um
so the uh the Americans could support
Armenia
and uh so there's a there's a whole lot
of options the Americans have and if
Turkey goes Rogue so to say then Armenia
also could you could see a escalation of
the conflict there also Georgia is a
pro-us nation I mean Georgia has had
these territorial disputes with Russia
they really fear Russia so the U.S could
use Georgia to you know ferment trouble
for turkey and to supply and Aid Armenia
and bolster its military capabilities so
it's a very complex situation and these
things could happen in the next five or
ten years
if the Turks feel that the U.S is
becoming weaker and other nations are
getting stronger and maybe they will
feel that now is the time to make our
move
so these possibilities are there
so yeah that's the kind of thing that
could happen turkey is extremely
important especially because of the two
choke points that it straddles between
the Mediterranean Mediterranean and the
Black Sea and of course all these other
issues so yeah many things could happen
and we can't really predict how it goes
but these are the possibilities
Christoph Becker says question from
Germany what role will other cultures
play after India and what the West calls
Hindu nationalism finally takes a
dominant Global position in the future
the interesting question see uh
in yeah the West always keeps on
bringing this alarm Bells but with what
it calls the Hindu nationalism hindut
nationalism all those things see Hindu
nationalism is very simple it's not uh
it's not expansionist it's it's uh it's
not a xenophobic it's not supremacist
Hindu nationalism is limited to a very
small thing it says that Indians I mean
you know uh what it it calls Hindu
nationalism is is the desire of the
Indian people to have a strong Sovereign
and Independent India and uh in India
that reclaims its lost territories
that's all if you look at I mean we know
what territories India has lost I I'm
not talking about the concept of akhand
Bharat over here I'm talking about Jammu
and Kashmir and Akshay chin and that
that's essentially all it is
so um so Indians desire a strong
independent powerful Sovereign
self-sufficient and and advanced India
and the West doesn't want this to happen
so it portrays this this these
aspirations of Indians as Hindu
nationalism Mr Modi has been one of the
most secular Prime Ministers you can
imagine and they keep on in any read any
uh article in the west about Mr Modi the
first thing they'll say is Hindu
nationalist yeah so so first of all
Hindu nationalism is a misnomer uh most
Indians are I mean they you know there
is no sentiment whatsoever of of India
being an expansionist nation and India
being a hegemonic nation that will
impose a one world order order over the
world
so first of all this this fear that many
people seem to have because of this mis
portrayal is completely unfounded
so now the question is let's say
hypothetically in the future maybe 20
years from now maybe 50 years from now
whenever it happens if it does whenever
India becomes uh the dominant force in
the world India takes a dominant
position in the world what role will
other cultures play so let's let's see
look at times in the past when this kind
of thing has happened uh in the past
five six thousand years there have been
times when India has been the most uh
economically India has always been the
most powerful Nation but at times India
has also been militarily very powerful
when it every time it has been unified
under a single Empire we can think of uh
the mauryan Empire The kushan Empire the
Gupta Empire in this later uh to some
extent under the Chola Empire which
actually was an expansionist empire for
some time so during these times what
happened
firstly India did not go and try to
conquer the entire world Indians Indian
Emperors never basically ventured beyond
the boundaries of the Indian
subcontinent the there are a couple of
exceptions one can think of
uh kanishka obviously he conquered much
of Central Asia and uh what is now
called xinjiang but there was no
cultural imposition or there was no
atrocities there was no brutality as
such yeah so that is the case then uh
during the Gupta Empire India did
conquered balika and all that which is
back to what is now called bactria the
Gandhara Tajikistan Turkmenistan region
so that was a brief period Then you had
lalitative who conquered large parts of
Central Asia and also Tibet and then you
had the cholas uh about a thousand years
from before today who conquered
essentially the entirety of Southeast
Asia all the way to the Philippines so
whenever these things have happened
the cultures that uh have been affected
by this have by no means uh been made to
to be to play a a secondary role or they
have not been subjugated India has never
ever been culturally hegemonic Nation
India's culture did spread far and wide
but it spread through peaceful means I
mean look at China China it may not
appear so today but China has been under
an enormous amount of Indian cultural
influence and this was done without
sending a single soldier across the
Himalayas Japan much of Japan's culture
is of Indian origin so the same is for
goes with South Korea Indonesia it's
it's the Golden Era of Indonesia's
history was when it was a Hindu Empire
the majapahit empire in Philippines and
all that
and yet you can see even if you go to
these places today you will see the
Indian elements of the culture and you
will see the uh the distinctive
indigenous culture also that's mixed
with it so India has never imposed
Culture by force India has never made
other nations and other cultures uh
force them to submit and pay tribute or
any such thing so in case India becomes
uh the dominant uh nation in the future
the dominant civilization again in the
future I don't think it's going to uh
affect any of the other cultures in any
uh negative way at all see India itself
is an extraordinarily diverse and
pluralistic civilization
if you travel 50 kilometers in India
just 50 kilometers the dialect changes
the cuisine changes the Traditions
change
and and it's an extremely diverse and
pluralistic place and yet it is all just
one culture in one civilization it's a
big umbrella called Indian culture in
Indian civilization it is despite all
these differences and extreme diversity
which seems to be very different
superficially it's still one culture and
one civilization so India is very much
used to diversity and pluralism and
that's what Indians really love
so India would not want the world to be
a monoculture today we have this
globalism movement which wants to trans
turn the entire world into a monoculture
everybody wears the same clothes
everybody has the same thoughts
everybody it's the same fries and
burgers and pizzas and that sort of
thing
that is horrible that will make the
world an extremely dull boring and
monochromatic place we want multi-colors
we want the world to be multiple colored
place so India is the epitome of this
India for thousands of years it had has
had hundreds maybe thousands of
languages and dialects and lots of
different local manifestations of its
culture and if India does become a
dominant culture the dominant uh
civilization I think there could be an
actual a fluorescence of more diversity
and pluralism in the world as compared
to the kind of monoculture that's there
are attempts to impose monocultural kind
of thing on the world from a couple of
different angles
so I think the opposite of that will
happen if India does take a dominant
Global position in the future I think
you will see in a fluorescence of of uh
diversity and pluralism in the world if
if India takes the leadership position
if it does happen so I you know so I
would say to our friends outside of
India that please uh they don't be
misled by all this propaganda about
Hindu nationalism uh indoorationalism
what they call Hindu nationalism is just
the desire and the aspiration of Indians
to see a strong United and Sovereign
India and that's it India has no
aspiration of taking over other nations
we have Nepal with which have we've had
this
very ancient relationship I mean Nepal
Nepal has been a sovereign state for the
past I don't know 200 300 years and uh
and we have this very interesting open
border system with Nepal so Nepal is a
very very much a Sovereign Nation but we
have an open border and the people of
Nepal have the right to work and live in
India and they also have the right to
serve in the Indian armed forces can you
imagine that allowing citizens of a
different country to serve in your Armed
Forces so that's how much trust in all
that is there with Nepal in the future
you could have this sort of thing with
Sri Lanka also India is never going to
try and take over Nepal next Nepal or
Sri Lanka or anything else
this is this is just fine the way it is
you know so I think if this if India
does take a global globally dominant
position in the future it's actually
going to be good for other cultures
India will never try to subjugate any
culture or or
indulge in cultural imperialism ever
it's never happened it will never happen
it's going to be good for the world if
if India does take a a dominant Global
position
okay siprakar says can you explain the
doctrine of Discovery very interesting
doctrine of Discovery so what was this
doctrine of Discovery the doctrine of
Discovery it's it's uh it's What's led
to colonialism and all the
the the destruction of native cultures
across the world by by the Europeans so
the doctrine of Discovery was a
principle of international law uh which
was used by European Colonial powers to
justify their expansionism and their
occupation of land in the Americas and
in other parts of the world Africa Asia
Etc
so what was this where does it originate
it originates with the church with the
Catholic Church the Vatican it I think
it was first uh
by
Pope in the 16th century I think it was
Nicholas the fifth or sixth or something
yeah this guy issued what's called papal
Bulls which are like decrees or laws
these papal Bulls granted European
rulers Kings the authority to claim
lands and and people and the people in
those lands as long as those lands and
people were not under Christian rule so
if you are let's say a native in the
Americas and you're not Christian then
you can be taken your line and your in
you yourself the people can be taken
over yeah so you become The Possession
the property of these European monarchs
and this was so this was given
sanctioned by the highest Christian
Authority the pope himself and then this
doctrine of Discovery was used to
justify European expansionism and
colonization by claiming that these
lands and people who are not under
Christian rule were discovered
and therefore they were occupy open to
occupation and exploitation by Europeans
so it's like you discover a new species
of animal and then it becomes yours
that's the kind of uh
attitude that was there and this
eventually became a principle of
international law it was used by
European Colonial powers to claim
territories like in in the Americas
North America South America the
Spaniards took over South America
and the French and the the British Etc
they and they fought over North America
the Spaniards also took Mexico and then
there was Africa there was Australia and
oh Asia also yeah so this doctrine of
Discovery was used to
usurp to seize lands from the indigenous
peoples the native peoples and to
completely disregard any notion of the
fact that they may have sovereignty and
ownership over the land totally
disregarded and see the plight of the
Native uh of the Australian Aboriginal
people today it's it's horrible and and
the Native Americans in North America
good God what atrocities they've
suffered yes so this doctrine of
Discovery denied these indigenous people
the right to their land and to their
culture also there was cultural genocide
all over the place these people were
treated as
Savages
as uncivilized primitive almost subhuman
people and it was uh taken as as
an undeniable fact that these people
should be subservient there was slavery
rampant slavery look what Christopher
Columbus did to the aravak people for
instance to the Carib people uh on the
island of Espanola which is now Haiti
and all that yep
um so this was a horrible thing it was
used to justify all kinds of
exploitation of the people of their
lands of the resources uh whatever
resources were on the land this led to
genocide extreme I mean widespread
violence multiple instances of genocide
enslavement and with the Europeans came
various diseases in the new world in the
Americas and all that so that's what the
doctrine of Discovery was now it's
interesting that there is this there was
this Supreme Court judge in the U.S
let's let's Google this lady shall we
Google
let me put this on the screen
not this
let me put something else on the screen
let's do a Google search about this
wonderful lady who they worship here
roots
Bader Ginsburg
it's Berg
all right now let's
add doctrine of discovery
doctrine of this
discovery so this lady who is a you know
portrait is a champion of of the
oppressed and of Human Rights and of
women and God knows what else she is
almost defied today she dies I think in
2020. let's take a look at this article
Ruth Bader ginsburg's notorious opinion
in the Native American sovereignty case
is also part of her Legacy she said your
lands were taken from you taken from you
illegally but there's nothing we can do
for you now history and the law are
written by
the winners
so the Oneida Indian Nation they were
trying to reclaim some lands in the
state of New York and uh so these these
people these Native Americans
they did not even have the right to uh
have any recourse to the law I think
until the 1970s until the 1970s they
don't even have the option of going to
the courts then they went to the court
in 97 98 or something
so somewhere around there right and they
uh petitioned the U.S
Supreme Court I think or whatever it was
Supreme Court yes and they they asked
for the right to the lands that were
stolen from them so this is what Ruth
Bader Ginsburg said given the
long-standing non-indian character of
the area and its inhabitants when she
says Indian it means Native Americans so
given the long-standing non-indian
character of the area and its
inhabitants the regulatory Authority
constantly exercised by New York state
in its counties and towns in the Oneida
Indians long delay in seeking judicial
relief against parties other than the
United States we hold the tribe cannot
unilaterally revive its ancient
sovereignty in whole or in part over the
parcels at issue it means too much time
has passed since everything went since
you were your land was stolen from you
so any remedy now after the passage of
time would be too disruptive it would
not be fair to the non-indian land
owners in the region uh and so on
so the tribe the court must prevent the
tribe from rekindling The Embers of
sovereignty that grew
that long ago grew cold
uh yeah courts were closed to these
people to the oneda Indian tribe until
1974. so how do you expect them to
pursue their legal claims
yeah
incredible incredible
so this world on the basis of the
discovery Doctrine doctrine of Discovery
so you can read this article it's it's a
horrible
tragedy what's what's be what's still
being done to the Native Americans in
the United States and across North
America yes uh so that's how it is
so yeah Justice Ginsburg seemed to say
your laws where your lands were taken
from you illegally illegally but even if
the law says those sales were of no are
of no effect there is nothing we can do
for you now it would not be fair not to
the white people who make up the
majority of the population in the claim
area this is how even today the Native
Americans are marginalized
and
it's clear that these lines were taken
from them illegally and still they are
they are not given any uh justice so
that is the doctrine of Discovery still
in action today it's not something
that's long dead it's still in action
today in the United States and maybe in
other English-speaking Nations as well
let's take a look at Australia maybe
Canada maybe elsewhere I'm I invite you
all to to do some research about this
I'm sure you'll find interesting
examples of more of the same so that's
the doctrine of discovery portable
Samir Naik says why did britishers
what's the britisher I call them the
British
we are not indianers right I don't know
Indians use this term all the time
britishers
anyhow that's that's different okay
let's go back to the question the
question
why did the British hand over the
Andaman and nicobar Islands to India
which is of Which is far away from India
but nearer to other countries
for instance Indonesia and Thailand in
Malaysia
and it has a huge Naval domain dominance
in that region for India asking this
question because the British wanted to
avoid the rise of India again
good question let's take a look at the
map to understand uh the
how far this is in case some of you
don't know I always like to open the map
where's the map here's the map
so this is where India I'm sure we all
know where it is and this here is the
Andaman and nicobar Islands north of the
andamans is the
yeah so this is the archipelago in in
question the southernmost island is this
one here great nicobar which is just
about how far is it from Indonesia I'm
sure it's less than
less than
yeah it's about 211 kilometers away from
Indonesia so it's very close to
Indonesia very close
so the question is why did the British
hand over these islands to India
when other countries are closer by like
such such as Indonesia
and uh
it obviously gave India a huge Advantage
Naval advantages in this region so
what's what's the reason what's the
cause that's the question it's a good
question so let's understand why the
British left India in 1947. do you think
they wanted to live in 1947 no they
obviously understood that now India is
no longer the cash cow it was we have
sucked everything all the blood of India
dry India has been totally destroyed
there's almost nothing left for us to
steal from India so there were they
actually wanted to leave India in a
proper step-by-step manner in a very
what you would call an orderly
withdrawal or orderly retreat but
something went wrong what after 90 after
the second World War
which ended in 1945 there was the events
of 1946 the the Great Indian Naval
Rebellion which spread like wildfire in
the Indian Navy just almost overnight
all of the ships in the Indian in the
British Indian Navy
they had rebelled against the British
crown
these ships were as far east as
Singapore and as far west as Oman
and obviously you had a bunch of ships
like seven eight ships maybe Seven Trips
uh naval ships warships in the Andaman
and nicobar Islands so this Mutiny star
they call it a mutiny it's a rebellion
it was a
so it started in Mumbai it spread to
Karachi in which other places and the
British not the British it was Mr Gandhi
the Great
Mr Gandhi was able to nip the rebellion
in the bud with the help of the great Mr
Patel
so let's not go into the history I have
a separate video about that on this
channel in case you are interested yes
so
what happened is that the Indian Navy
the British Indian Navy which was
stationed in the andamanic nicobar
islands it participated in support in in
this Rebellion it supported the
Rebellion the British realized that it's
you know the Indian Navy can control
these islands easily and no matter what
we do the Indians once they take control
of the Navy uh they'll be able to retain
this Islands
in 1946 sent the British in a panic they
realized that if the Armed Forces
rebelled properly the British rule over
India will be over in about 24 hours in
in a very bloody way that's why they
were so Hasty in getting out of India
and they left India by 15th of August
1947 very rapidly it was not the
original plan
so they were not able to break India
properly into multiple places like they
would have liked to do right this 1946
Rebellion
uh it it made them
leave India very hastily
so that's one reason and uh the Indian
Navy was very capable of Defending these
islands and historically you see
understand this that historically no
other nation has ever had a claim on
these islands
uh but historically India has used these
islands from time to time the cholas
used they they used these islands as a
staging post for their Naval invasion of
of Indonesia
so the Chulas a thousand years ago were
using these islands the marathas the
great uh maratha Admiral kanoji angre he
also used these islands as a staging
post for his Navy
uh
during the second world war the Azad
Hindi Forge the Indian national Army was
in possession of these islands nominally
it was actually the Japanese that
occupied the islands but it was
nominally in the hands of the uh
of the
Japanese so India has always used and a
head possession and claim on these
islands the British would have liked to
break India more and maybe
hand over these islands perhaps to
Indonesia perhaps to somebody else but
they were no longer in a position to do
that
so and the other thing is that none of
these other nations the so-called the
neighboring Nations like Indonesia
Malaysia Singapore Thailand Myanmar none
of these nations made any claim to the
island to these islands they all
accepted the fact that these Islands
belong to India they have never disputed
this uh in 1965 the Indonesians tried to
place a Mischief but the Indian Navy was
very strong in this region so yeah the
Indonesians supported Pakistan in 1965.
and it seems that they had sent you know
reconnaissance parties of their Navy
into the region but the Indian Navy was
very strongly present and the
Indonesians could do nothing
so these are the reasons why the British
where they had no option but to hand
over the undercover Islands to India
because India would have anyway taken
over the islands whether they liked it
or not so it was essentially a faith
accompli and
that's what happened
all right let's take the next question
says why did this Somalia Ethiopia War
happen
what roles did the two superpowers in
their allies play in this conflict did
this war pave the way for Malia's
financial and political crisis very
interesting question Somalia so let's
once again take a look at the map
to understand the context
so where is Somalia we know where India
is go go westwards and cross the
sea and here we are at the Horn of
Africa this region is called The Horn of
Africa it's essentially Somalia Ethiopia
Eritrea Djibouti that's what it is
that's that is the Horn of Africa so
this war happened in the late 1970s I
think uh
1977-78 if I'm not mistaken that time
period
and uh at that time
Ethiopia was ruled by uh a bunch of army
generals or Army it was ruled by the
Army and it was under Army Rule and it
was a Marxist Nation
Ethiopia at the time and Somalia was at
the time a socialist Nation at that time
Ethiopia was supported by the USSR and
Somalia was supported by the United
States the U.S was supporting Somalia at
the time in the 19 in the late 1970s so
there was this uh disputed region called
ogaden where is oga then well it shows
on Google Maps oh God then
here we are okay can you see this the
highlighted region that is called ugadin
I'm not sure about the exact
pronunciation is but you get the meaning
so this region
was under dispute because it it was a
Somali majority region most of the
people the majority of the people in
this region were of Somalian ethnicity
but this region was under Ethiopian
control and that was the dispute it is
still under Ethiopian control so that
was the dispute and the somalis and this
was also a geopolitical thing it was
also part of the Cold War the Americans
were supporting Somalia this USSR was
supporting Ethiopia and both these
superpowers were vying for were jousting
for influence in Africa as well so this
essentially became kind of a proxy war
this I think the Somalians were the
first they they fired the first shots
they invaded the garden region then they
took over much of it and then the
Ethiopians responded they retaliated and
the USSR sent in lots of supplies arms
ammunition weapon systems the Cubans
under Fidel Castro sent more than 10 000
troops with all kinds of weapons and all
that and because of this foreign
assistance the Ethiopians were able to
repossess the territory that the
Somalians had taken over
and the outcome of the war was that
Somalia lost this conflict Ethiopia won
even today you can see that this
straight line boundary which is very
typical of Africa is a dashed line on
Google Maps which tells you that this is
still a disputed boundary
uh so that is what the war was it was
about this ugaden region disputed region
the Ethiopians won because of USSR and
and and Cuba's support
and this was a victory for for the USSR
essentially in in the Cold War
um so that is the rule that the two
superpowers and their allies played in
this conflict now this war like you say
yes it did pave eventually for somalia's
financial and political crisis so the
Somalian government uh so because of
this war because of the intense
militarization of this entire region you
had lots of different militias that that
popped up in Somalia who were all
fighting for the the freedom from
Ethiopia of the ugaden region so there
was the appearance of multiple centers
of power which is never good when they
are all armed yes and obviously because
of the war there was this extreme
there was a there was this uh economic
crisis and the the economy of the region
went into the doldrums it uh of both the
Nations suffered a lot in Ethiopia there
was this very major famine in the 1980s
I think 1984 1985 it was terrible
so that's the kind of situation you had
and Somalia also was greatly
impoverished and you know in in
geopolitics there is a significant delay
between cause and effect in any sport in
anything there is a delay between cause
and effect so in this case there was a
delay of about 14 years and in 1991
eventually the government of Somalia
collapsed and Somalia descended into
Civil War and the Americans tried to
intervene there was this warlord called
Muhammad Farah ideas the Americans uh
sent their troops to Mogadishu there was
this terrible Battle of battle of
Mogadishu in which I don't know more
than a thousand Somalian civilians were
massacred by the American troops but the
Somalians were able to take a few
Americans prisoner and I think they were
killed or whatever and their bodies were
dragged over the streets and it came on
the cover of Time Magazine a disaster
for the Americans it was during the
Clinton Administration so these are the
things that happened and I I would say
that certainly it's this war the ogadan
war of 1978 and 1977-78 that paved the
way that that started a chain of events
that led to the uh to the fall of the
Somalian government and the and and The
Descent of Somalia into Civil War and
Somalia even today you know it's it's
kind of a lawless place and it's
extremely uh it's it's an extremely hard
life if you are a Somalian citizen so
all of this started around that time
so yes a very interesting question that
rodrigit has asked
Krishna saraf says I started reading the
Unabomber Manifesto and I have come to
really agree with Ted Kaczynski what are
your your opinions about his theory
interesting question I'm not sure I have
discussed the Unabomber Ted Kaczynski
let's Google
Ted Kaczynski shall we give me a second
let's put that on the screen and I'll
let's talk about it so Ted Kaczynski was
a mathematical genius it was a
mathematics professor he was a genius
let's Google him dead
I hope that's a spelling that is indeed
the spelling
his name is he is
still alive his name is Theodore John
kazinski the Unabomber
um so he was a he is a mathematical
genius he is a former mathematics
professor uh
he was in University of California
Berkeley he became an assistant
professor I believe at the age of 25 he
wrote multiple research papers very high
quality research papers in mathematics
I'm sure you can find these research
papers online
and obviously he also wrote the
Unabomber Manifesto and I'm sure you can
find it online let's Google it you know
bomber
any
Festival
here it is I'm not sure if you yeah here
it is you can actually read the entire
text it's about 25 or 35 000 words
and the top the title of this is
industrial society and its future so
that's about Ted Kaczynski now the
question that uh
Krishna has asked is I started reading
this unibomber Manifesto and I've come
to agree with Ted Kaczynski so you know
lots of people agree with this Manifesto
it's a very well written Manifesto with
extremely good arguments and these are
the arguments not of a Madman but of a
very intelligent person let's see what
the uh Manifesto what what people have
said about it
um
yeah
somebody from the New York Times wrote
that if this is the work of a Madman
then the works of then the writings of
many political philosophers like
Rousseau Payne and Marx are scarcely
more sane so he's saying that this is
the work of a very intelligent man it's
not the work of a Madman this is not
Madness right so what so you can read
the manifesto you just have to Google it
so what did did kazinski say what what
what what what are the what is the core
uh
thought process or philosophy or the the
central arguments of the manifesto first
of all he says that he criticizes
modern society he criticizes the effects
of modern technology on society he he
says that industrial society is
fundamentally unjust and oppressive so
this sounds like what Karl Marx said
doesn't it but Ted Kaczynski was
anti-left he was not a Marxist he was
empty left so he believed definitely
that industrial society is fundamentally
unjust and oppressive and he called he
also called for a revolution Ted
Kaczynski he called for a revolution to
overthrow the current system and
establish a more simpler a new way of
life a simpler way of life
not a revolution of the proletariat in
which there will be a dictatorship of
the proletariat and the new society
which is all egalitarian everybody has
the community Society he did not ask for
that he wanted to have a simpler way of
life which is closer to Nature that's
the that's what he wanted and he said
that industrial society is reducing the
quality of life for individuals and it's
also causing environmental Distortion
which is completely correct
it is very true both these arguments are
true that industrial society is reducing
the quality of life for individuals in
the past people were so much closer to
Nature the pace of life was much slower
people had more time for contemplation
for family for scholarly Pursuits or
whatever trade they were there were
indulging in
today life is so fast and you know
quality of life has deteriorated and
obviously there's a lot of environmental
damage and destruction and he said that
uh
the rise of technology has led to an
increase in psychological and physical
suffering well I think the statistics
will show you that this is indeed true
the rise of technology has led to an
increase in in mental illness and
depression and various psychological uh
problems and also physical suffering
people have become more sedentary rise
of the rise of lifestyle diseases like
coronal coronary heart disease and and
diabetes and much more so all of this is
a consequence of the rise of Technology
and uh Ted Kaczynski criticized the
spread of
technological influence including the
media and the government he also said
that uh
technological he also argued that
technological progress is not inevitable
it can be stopped it can even be
reversed he was not anti-technology but
he was about keeping society and human
life Closer To Nature and not make it so
uh wired to technology
the one of the controversial things that
he says is he called for
um a reduction in the in the size of the
human population through voluntary means
not through what Karl Marx or Stalin or
Mao would have done but through
voluntary means so maybe a slow gradual
decline in the population not some
abrupt drastic thing
and uh
and the other thing he wrote about is
that he believed that the current
economic system and the current
political system is controlled by a very
small and very elite group of people
I think lots of people believe this
today and I think there is evidence that
suggests that this may indeed this may
indeed be true we call it the Deep State
and what the some people like to call it
the Illuminati or whatever so Ted
Kaczynski was was of the opinion that
this is the case a very small Elite
group of people essentially control the
political system of the world and the
economic system of the world essentially
they run the whole world a small number
of people maybe a hundred people maybe
one maybe 150 people you will even see
saying the same thing
so yeah so Ted Kaczynski was was of this
opinion
um so he essentially said that the
Industrial Revolution was a major
turning point in human history and
he said that a new Revolution is
necessary to save Humanity otherwise we
are on the path to destruction so it's
kind of gloomy and kind of pessimistic
and he said that A revolution is
necessary otherwise we will be on the
path of discussion so essentially this
is the Unabomber Manifesto industrial
society and uh what is it called the the
um
yeah so that's the Yuna bomber Manifesto
uh industrial society in its future so I
don't think this is the work of a Madman
I think this is the work of a very
intelligent mind you may or may not
agree with everything Ted Kaczynski said
but most of it is unreliably true and
it's all backed up by evidence and
statistics it's not a theory it's not
some of it is well
theoretical so if you want to if you
want to call it so but overall he wanted
a better future for the world he was
very concerned about the direction in
which the planet is going and it's it's
ever since it was apprehended things
have become much worse so the thing
about him is that he kind of went rogue
and he became a domestic terrorist he
sent these male bombs to universities uh
and the airports somewhere else I'm not
sure of you and it killed a few people
he was living in isolation in a cabin in
the woods and it's his brother I believe
who eventually became suspicious and
notified the U.S authorities and they
eventually caught him apprehended him
and they discovered yes it is indeed
this guy who is the Unabomber and he is
now in jail I think he must be around 80
years old
so that's the deal so I don't think um
you know I don't think he was entirely a
Madman this Manifesto makes a huge
amount of sense
um so yeah that's that's my opinion
about this
karun bihari says is it possible to
modify the DNA of living humans and
solve various uh inheritable health and
mental issues right away skin disorders
depression Etc is it already happening
greetings from the Netherlands crispr
what is crispr let's let's uh Google
crispr it's a gene editing technology
it's a revolutionary technology that has
totally transformed
um
transform the world essentially it's on
the verge of transforming the world what
is crispr
c-r-i-s-p-r crispr
clustered regularly into spaced short
palindromic repeats so that's what it is
you can you can Google it that's what it
is so crispr is a gene editing
technology it allows
whoever uses it to very uh precisely
change or edit the DNA of of an organism
so it can be used to to create
genetically modified organisms GMOs you
can uh use crispr to introduce certain
um characteristics in let's say a crop
in wheat or rice or any other any other
plant you can use it to introduce or to
to change the DNA and characteristics of
various organisms like insects or even
human beings
uh it is indeed possible to use crispr
to solve certain
health problems there are certain uh
certain mental health issues let's say
schizophrenia
which are indeed inherited from uh
parent to child one of the most famous
examples is the great mathematician John
Nash John Forbes Nash who was a
schizophrenic and he was and
schizophrenia is this condition in which
people experience hallucinations they
hear voices they kind of start living in
an alternative alternate reality and
they kind of lose touch with the real
world it's extremely it's extremely uh
severe in some cases and it kind of
passes from parent to child so John
Forbes Nash who eventually was able to
overcome this and win the Nobel Prize
his son is also a mathematician he also
has schizophrenia so the thing is I'm
not sure we have discovered the set of
genes or whatever it is that that causes
schizophrenia it's clearly something
that's inherited so it has to have a
genetic component but we haven't
discovered as far as I know the specific
Gene sequences that cause schizophrenia
if it is discovered then it may be
possible to use it will if it is
discovered then it will be possible to
use crispr to edit that those sections
those segments of the DNA and possibly
end the problem
and there are various illnesses also
that are inheritable and all so if if uh
one can determine pinpoint the exact
genetic sequences in the D if in the
human genome where which lead to this
disease then it was it is certainly
possible to
edit and remove them so it is possible
today to do these things uh
the thing is
the thing is that it crispr also can be
used for other things it can be used to
create designer babies which is
problematic let's say uh you have a
couple who are expecting a child and
they want that child to be so much feet
tall maybe six feet tall if it's a boy
or whatever I'm just it's all
hypothetical here let's say you want
your child to be at least six feet tall
let's say you want your child to have
green eyes let's say you want your child
to have
red hair let's say you want your child
to have this specific shade of skin
color
and let's say you want your child to be
extremely muscular or whatever of high
percentage of of fast twitch muscle
fibers whatever you know so you could do
all this eventually with crispr so that
raises a lot of ethical issues are we
playing God and whatever modifications
we are making are we sure that they will
not have
uh adverse effects Downstream seven
eight ten Generations Downstream when
you can no longer control what's
happening and
it also will
create a big divide in society between
those who are rich enough to afford this
and those who are left out so the rich
will ensure that their descendants
become are genetically superior to the
poor people and then that will cause
this incredible divide in society so
there are all these ethical issues in
crispr
but indeed it is already definitely
possible to modify to edit precisely the
DNA of human beings and introduce
various characteristics or remove
characteristics it is possible today
it's already happening and uh yeah so
yeah that's where we are today and this
these technologies will only
become more advanced as the years go by
Priyanka says good evening good evening
uh what's the future of nanotechnology I
took this subject in my Master's Degree
and it was quite interesting so I read a
lot and I thought that it's going to
revolutionize everything in the near
future but I don't see much practical
progress so far I guess it's been slow
what are my thoughts about this so
nanotechnology is is it's actually the
future progress may not be that visible
see whenever a new technology comes in
into the well whenever a new technology
appears it is first appropriated by the
military
and it is used for various military
purposes and eventually a few decades
later the spin-offs of that technology
trickle down into the civilian domain
so
so human we and there may be some
technologies around that we may not even
realize are because of nanotechnology so
nanotechnology is is the manipulation of
materials and substances if the Nano
scale nanoscale not the quantum scale
but the Nano scale so first of all you
have medicine and Healthcare
nanotechnology will revolutionize
medicine and Healthcare it will lead to
the development of all kinds of new more
effective diagnostic tools and
treatments and drugs for diseases it
will we can create Advanced Materials
and devices using nanotechnology
let's say you want to create an
extremely strong material which is
extremely light
today the strongest materials are
typically metals like steel and all that
but they're quite heavy but what if you
have a material that is stronger than
this than steel but let's say a third of
the weight that would be wonderful you
can have all kinds of wonderful
applications of that so high strength
and low weight that sort of thing so
that's the kind of Advanced Materials
you can create with nanotechnology you
can create a nano devices consumer
electronics you can create Nanobots that
can go into your bloodstream and clean
out whatever cloths or plaque you may
have in the heart you know that's thing
um
clean energy
more effective more efficient methods of
energy production and energy storage you
know better lithium ion batteries or
maybe batteries of other types that we
could create using my nanotechnology
batteries that can store more charge and
for a longer duration this will help us
reduce our dependence on fossil fuels
and mitigate the effects of climate
change all that
um
technology for water purification uh
more efficient methods of water
purification we can use a nanotechnology
for cleaning up pollution let's say you
have an oil spill in in the ocean which
happens from time to time oil spills so
let's so what about creating a
nanotechnology solution to cleaning up
an oil spin spill cleaning up pollution
Etc then obviously nanotechnology has a
uh applications in Computing increasing
computing power more advanced computer
systems right now we have the Silicon
Wafers that are just one level deep but
you could have entire stacks of this if
you can master that if of course the
heat is an issue but yes this will
eventually happen then uh space
exploration food production there are so
many applications and of course all of
this has military applications so I
think there is a huge amount of
potential in nanotechnology even to let
once again when it comes to military
applications air jet engines jet in jet
turbines jet turbine when you have a jet
engine let's say a fighter jet let's say
let's say any fighter jet whether that
travels the flies at Mach 2 twice the
speed of sound these jet engines become
extraordinarily hot thousands of degrees
Celsius and no matter how hard your or
strongest steel is steel is it's going
to melt so you need special materials
for that and you could create those
using nanotechnology so all of this is
going to happen through nanotechnology
the progress may not be that visible
because typically this technology comes
wrapped up in something else and it
doesn't you cannot really tell
that it's based on nanotechnology but
yeah
there's a lot of work happening in our
technology
um and eventually we will realize in 10
20 years that much of the progress may
have actually uh been Thanks to Nano
Technology it's very interesting it's a
very interesting subject and it's
typically in India I think it's taught
in various iits Indian institutions of
Technology
so yeah that's what it is the future is
great for nanotechnology maybe the way
that teachers teach it and all that is
kind of not so fascinating that's what
teachers typically end up doing in India
but I think the future is great for this
field
Nishant says
the ancient
1500 year sorry the ancient 11 500 year
old site
located in modern day Turkey is said to
be the oldest known proto-city in the
world my question is
is there any other proto-city or
settlement in the Indian subcontinent
which was older than this one which is
backed by actual historical and
archaeological evidence excellent
question I'm not sure we have discussed
so let us discuss go back to the way
let's go to that where is the map
here is the map and the map should be
now on the screen okay
let's go to go big clitipe we have to go
to Turkey it's actually quite close to
Syria in eastern Anatolia now I will not
be able to locate it unless I search for
it so go big
and zoom let's go in there
and here we are so let's first zoom out
and Orient ourselves where is it
yes it is indeed close to Syria now
let's zoom in and let's take a look at
this play this this uh archaeological
site for once and then let's discuss
what the question is
so here it is this is the archaeological
site of gobeklithepe
now let's see the size of this
archaeological site how big is it
so let's uh do a measurement of distance
from one end to another I'm taking a
larger distance than than is necessary
it's about 300 meters
so let's say this is a
from from east to west 300 meters and
North to South 300 meters so you can see
it's a very small thing and the actual
side is much smaller it's under this
Dome so that is barely
let's say the distance
it's barely 50 meters
50 meters and over here it is yeah
it's it's approximately a circle which
with a radius with a diameter of 55
meters that's all the archaeological
side is and if you want to take the
larger area around it it's about 300
meters in diameter that's all it is so
this is not a proto-sitting it's just
one archaeological site it looks like it
was some kind of Temple or or or some
kind of place of worship or something
maybe a religious site it was by no
means a city or even a town or even a
village it's just one small
archaeological site yes it is indeed uh
dated to be about 11 500 years old so
it's not a proposity it's just an
archaeological site and uh so that's the
deal let's zoom out there it is let's go
basically they pay now let's come back
to India and the question is is there
any old forget about Proto city is there
any other older archaeological site in
India so when it comes to the Saraswati
Sindhu phase of our history the oldest
known archaeological site is birana in
haryana which is dated to about uh
about 9 500 years before today so they
did carbon dating and the oldest samples
were 9 500 years old which dates back to
about 7500 BC so that's the oldest known
Saraswati Sindhu archaeological site in
India
but we know that there are thousands of
unexplored archaeological sites along
the dry River bed of the Saraswati and
along the Indus and other river banks
also in this region so
there are thousands of sites that our
archaeologists have not even explored
thus far so I think it's highly likely
first of all that there could be much
older archaeological sites in the
Saraswati Hindu region in this region
and maybe in other parts of India as
well now let's come to other parts of
India let's talk about uh let's go to
Southern India
uh so between puducherry and Chennai uh
the ASI I don't know it's the ASR who
else it is but Indian archaeologists
have been doing underwater archeology
over here in just last month in January
they announced the discovery of a
submerged City
uh about 80 kilometers or so north of
puducherry in the Sea Under the Sea it
is at a depth of between 50 to 100
meters and this city this ancient
submerged city is spread out over an
area of approximately 250 square
kilometers it's a large archaeological
site it's
it's the preliminary investigations show
that it's it could be about 10 000 years
old if not older and it looks like they
have rediscovered the lost city of
kaveri of the first sangam period
and the first some sangam period dates
back to 11 500 years before today if not
older yes so
we need to see more data come out of
kaveri pumpatinum which seems to be
coverednam but if it is so then this
could be definitely older than uh then
go back now let's come to uh where is it
dwaraka
so dwarka we know that this city has
been discovered rediscovered it's off
the coast of of the present day dwarka
the Mahabharata dwarka city is submerged
off the coast because obviously
obviously of uh global warming and and a
tectonic event an earthquake which was
described by Arjuna he witnessed this
happened the city being swallowed by the
by the Sea so this city they found a
piece of wood over there which is about
eight and a half thousand years old
so there again we have an old city and
more interesting thing is the Gulf of
kambat
so this city here is the Old Port of
kambat in Gujarat and this entire region
is called the Gulf of kambath and they
have archaeologists Indian
archaeologists have discovered an entire
network an entire complex of multiple
ancient cities submerged in the Gulf of
khambat it's an entire archaeological
complex of multiple cities and these
cities are laid out in exactly the same
manner as the great cities of the
Saraswati Hindu civilization like
mohenjo daro harappa rakhi gari and uh
Kali bangan Etc the same grid system the
great grid structure of streets in the
same style so these cities that are
underwater in the Gulf of hambad are in
the same style and they have the same
exact same characteristics as the
so-called Harappan cities now this this
archaeological complex is at a depth of
about 80 or 100 meters under the ocean
and the last time this this
that portion of the of the
of the bottom of the ocean was above
water was around 9 000 or so years
before today because of global warming
the sea Rose in these cities was
followed by the sea
and most likely these cities could be
older so these cities could possibly be
12 000 years old or older but the thing
is our archaeologists are not doing
their job go ahead send underwater
explorers pick up some pieces of pick up
some artifacts date them and tell us
what date it is I just don't understand
why there is nothing no work being done
in the submerged city of dwarka or in
the Gulf of combat archaeological
complex which was discovered more than
20 years ago nothing is being done there
the ASI has the money the ASI has the
Personnel but they are not doing this
for whatever reason so because our
archaeologists are not doing
what we are paying them to do that's why
we don't know
if there are older cities in India older
than Google I promise you there will be
so that's why I keep saying we need to
disband the ASI entirely
shut it down and create a new
organization a professional organization
of professional archaeologists from
scratch young people who are driven and
who are fascinated and curious and
obsessed with archeology pay them well
give them the funds and the resources
and see what they find but we're not
doing it
anyhow so that's the deal yeah so that's
what that's the answer I can give you
okay descendant of rigvedic Clans says
in the Saraswati Hindu civilization both
cremation and burials are found
including yet and and all that and uh
culture which has ruins of forts temples
Etc it's closely related culture to
Saraswati Sindhu civilization people so
maybe it's also possible that the
Saraswati and those civilization people
also built fourth temples Etc what's
your thoughts on this interesting
question so what is this uh
culture it's also called the Helmand
culture let's Google it
okay
let us Google that give me a second let
me place that on the screen
and we're going to Google
mandigak culture which is also called
helmond culture
right so the Wikipedia will say article
will say hell month culture first let's
look at the images
okay let's go
let's first go to the Wikipedia article
as always let me remind you all
Wikipedia is not necessarily a reliable
source of information especially when it
comes to Indian history I'm just putting
this over here for reference but do not
ever believe Wikipedia 100 and I'm going
to close this all right
so yeah the hell month culture which is
which dates back to 3300 BC
is the Bronze Age culture that
flourished in the hellmann valley it's
essentially Afghanistan Tajikistan
Turkmenistan Gandara and westwards
that's what it was and this culture
dates back to about 3300 BC
and yeah it does say that these people
had cities and temples and palaces a
complex and advanced social culture so
if you have temples and palaces and all
that you have advanced culture if you
don't have temples and palaces then you
are backward culture even if you are
fully urbanized weird so the main cities
are in Iran and mundika in Afghanistan
or these cities of the same culture and
all that
um what else does it say
it says there are there are also a few
connections with the Indus Valley
Civilization but it seems that the
hellmann civilization was earlier this
is what Wikipedia did as I'm showing you
in real time where Wikipedia is lying to
you okay
it says that the hellmann civilization
was earlier and did not overlap
chronologically very much with the
cities of the Indus Valley that's what
it says yeah hellmann civilization the
the Helmand culture begins 3300 BC yes
now let's Google something interesting
um
that's Google mature let's see what
Wikipedia itself has to say
periodization of the Indus Valley
Civilization
so remember Hell month culture it says
was 3300 BC
so what is early mature Harappan it's
4500 BC which is way before hellmann
culture and yet the other article says
that there was no overlap between
Hillman culture and in this Valley
culture what utter nonsense
so there you have in real time I'm
showing you how Wikipedia lies to you
and the Harappan culture actually the
so-called Harappan culture begins around
7500 BC they call it pre-harup or
whatever you could give any name you
want but it's the same culture it's the
same cultural continuity that begins
around 7500 BC almost 10 000 years
before today so what they call Harappan
culture clearly predates the so-called
Hillman culture and it is definitely it
was contemporaneous with hellmann
culture the so-called Harappan culture
well it still exists over here in India
we are all descendants of the same
culture the same civilization it never
ended it merely dispersed in different
parts of of India and elsewhere also
Helmand culture
ended around 2350 BC
apparently it ended
um so now let's take a look at hellmann
culture and what it looks like let's
take a look at the pottery shall we
so yeah it had these big columns
Monumental architecture you can see this
yeah
you can see this statue of a person or
carved head you can see these various
utensils the the face of a bull
let's go there
um
now this is exactly the same kind of
statuettes and figurines you find in the
Saraswati Sindhu region you also find in
mundigak and still they are saying there
is no connection or very little
connection here is more you find exactly
the same thing this again there you go
a bull it's an Indus Valley bull it's
it's a Harappan ball it's an Indian bull
the same bull here this is again mundika
look at the pottery you find the exact
same Pottery in the saraspatis Hindu
archaeological sites the same Pottery
the same patterns the same style the
same stylistic elements
yeah uh the same uh leaves even the same
leaves
so what this tells you
is that most likely the mandika culture
or the hellmann culture was nothing but
but an offshoot
or a border area of these Saraswati
Sindhu civilization era
and since these people
uh the mundikat people had uh temples
and Forts and palaces it tells us that
the the people of the Saraswati Hindu
era in some places had this so let's
take a look at the map and see where
this is and all that
let's find that let's go back to our
trusty old
map
so where is
it is let me Google that
is
the dry City or the burn City
that's what they say in Persian so as
you can see it is uh west of present-day
Afghanistan it is in the extended
Gandara region
and other sites have been found in
Northern Afghanistan even Tajikistan
even turkistan
so
so what we see is that when Indian
people move into Central Asia and all
these deserted regions their culture
changes their behavior changes the
Traditions change maybe when you live in
this sort of environment you need you
need forts
because that's a dangerous inhospitable
terrain and maybe you have
maybe you have other tribes who live
there who are not very friendly with you
and maybe resources are so scarce that
people have to fight each other for
small resources so maybe when you live
in places like this you need to build
forts
and maybe that also causes a
YouTube build temples or whatever so
this is this is all speculation but what
is very clear from the evidence that we
just saw of the pottery and the art and
the sculpture and the statuettes the
figurines is that the mundika culture is
it shows the same cultural and artistic
characteristics as the Saraswati Sindhu
culture
so yeah so like uh this uh the the
person descended a frigbedic clan says
it is certainly possible that the
Saraswati Sandhu people
did build forts palaces temples but when
they lived in these far off regions not
in not in the Sarasota region not in the
saptasindhu region
okay let's take some more questions
Sharma is Big says who was the best
Roman Emperor according to me and who do
you think and do you think there was any
Roman emperor that could be comparable
to chatrapati shivaji Maharaj or
Maharana Pratap or when he where any of
them really that great uh thank you
um
best Roman Emperor how do you define
this first of all we have to Define best
do we mean the Roman Emperor who
conquered the most territory do we mean
the Roman Emperor who uh made Rome the
most prosperous do we mean the person
who was the most uh peaceful
so I'm not sure what is the Criterion
for the best Roman Emperor uh maybe the
most successful so obviously one has to
think of Augustus
Augustus was the first Roman Emperor and
he ruled for I don't know how many years
40 more than 40 years if I'm not
mistaken
and there were Decades of Civil War in
Rome after the reign of Julius Caesar
and all that stuff so Augustus
stabilized the Roman Empire
and he brought in stability political
stability and he uh indulged in various
military conquests he expanded the
territory of the Roman Empire he also
established a very stable system of
government that in that system lasted
for centuries essentially and uh he also
had a significant cultural effect he did
social reforms and social programs
building of various uh projects public
works like aqueducts temples all that so
Augustus has to be one of the great
Roman emperors then you have the Roman
Emperor trajan
t-r-a-j-a-n who uh
expanded the Roman Empire eastwards he
conquered what's what is what was then
called Dacia Dacia which is roughly
present day Romania he also did lots of
Public Works and built roads and uh
aqueducts and temples and all that so uh
during uh trajan's time I think the
Roman Empire expanded to its greatest
extent and there were there was a huge
amount of very high degree of prosperity
very great interconnectedness of the
entire region through roads and all that
so overall for the citizens who were not
slaves it was a great time during
trajan's time then you had Hadrian who I
believe succeeded trajan so Hadrian
conquered the West trajan went all the
way to Romania and conquered Romania
Hadrian conquered more of the British
Islands including Scotland and he is
famous for the construction of the
hadrians Hadrian's Wall would you like
to see Hadrian's Wall it still stands in
some places let's take a look at
Hadrian's Wall let us Google that
Hadrian's Wall
Hadrian's Wall so it's still there in
parts
and it still stands
you can see this is Hadrian's Wall so
this was uh the the northernmost if I'm
not mistaken extent of the Roman Empire
this was in Scotland and it it still
stands
to a large degree this is how it would
have looked like in the past yes so so
that's what Hadrian did he uh built this
he built this wall which helped secure
the northern part of the northern
Frontier of the Roman Empire
he conquered parts of Scotland he
established a stable rule over the
British islands and obviously he did
lots of Public Works he was a patron of
the Arts and Sciences and did
constructed libraries and temples and
baths and Roads and overall it improved
the quality of life for Roman citizens
who were not slaves even one has to keep
specifying that then you had Marcus
Aurelius the great philosopher Emperor
who expanded the empire northwards into
Germania
yes so he was known for his leadership
during various during a time of various
military crises and he is also the
author of The meditations
stoicism a series of personal
Reflections and moral guidance so Marcus
auridius was successful in maintaining
the stability and prosperity of the
Empire as long as he was alive one could
also throw in the name of Constantine
the Great
the first Roman Emperor to convert to
Christianity he essentially founded or
he didn't
he
wasn't the founder of the uh
Eastern Roman emperor empire but he
played a significant role in that so he
established the new capital of
Constantinople named after him during
his lifetime it was called byzantion
but after he died it was called
Constantinople
so this was the beginning of the
Byzantine Empire essentially and the
beginning of the rise of Christianity so
Constantine well was a very successful
Emperor if you were to see an example of
a not so successful Emperor let me show
you this one give me a second
his name was Ella gabalus
take a look at this
so this guy
his name was Marcus Aurelius Antonios
also known as Ella gabalus or Helio
gabalus he was a Roman Emperor for four
years between 2018 and 2022. he was the
weirdest guy you can ever imagine and uh
if you want to know about him he was
eventually killed by his own Soldiers by
the Roman pretorian guard guard if I'm
not mistaken he and his mother both
and then his aunt took over or something
like that it's a very fascinating story
and yeah this is this is an example of a
not so great emperor of one of the worst
Emperors so when times go when when an
Empire starts
uh goes into decline then you have such
weird Emperor to turn up which you may
see in other places in the world today
also so look it up if you are so
interested if you're interested in that
is like asking whether uh whether uh
whether
Hannibal Barca was Tunisian
there was no Tunisia
during the time of Hannibal Barka
and similarly there was no there were no
pashtoons and there was no Afghanistan
during the time of the Mahabharata when
shakuni and gandhari were alive
so their descendants and their the
descendants of their and their relatives
who still live today are definitely
pursues
so shakuni and gandari who are siblings
who were siblings were from the northern
mahajanapada of gandhar which is now
Afghanistan that region
but they were not pashto's
identity arose way way way later most
likely during the uh turkification of
Afghanistan
when Afghanistan finally became
islamized it's around that time that the
pashtun identity became a thing it's
like it's like asking whether um
there was no rajput identitated in the
Mahabharat time the rajput that entity
emerged much much later yes the the
rajput Clans are all more or less the
descendants of the royal Clans the
aristocratic clans of the mahajanapada
Iran maybe the late vedikira also but
there was no rajput identity then then
during that time and similarly during
the Mahabharata time there was no
pashtun identity they were just people
of kandar
so yeah that's the answer
pushpendra Singh says what are your
views on the finding of 92 closely
located dinosaur nests in 256 fossilized
eggs of herbivorous titanosaurs one of
the largest known dinosaurs which has
been found by a team of paleontologists
in their District part of the narmada
valley my view is that it's wonderful
it's not surprised that they have found
such a thing India was home to God knows
how many species of dinosaurs India was
a hotbed of dinosaur activity up until
66 million years ago when we know what
happened the impact and when this impact
happened that killed off the non-avian
dinosaurs at the time India was an
island
in
in the Indian Ocean do you know that
let's take a look
um
let's go back to the map the trusty old
map
so
this is the map so you can see this
island over here of the eastern coast of
Africa it's called Madagascar and you
can see the shape of Madagascar kind of
fits with the shape of Africa over here
like a jigsaw puzzle it's because
Madagascar at about 120 million years
ago was part of the coastline of Africa
and so was the Peninsular part of India
you can see the Northern tip of
Madagascar can perfectly fit into the
neck of Gujarat
so you can see it's all part of a jigsaw
puzzle so because of tectonic activity
India and Madagascar detached from
Africa Madagascar stayed stayed behind
in India shot all the way across the
Indian Ocean and slammed into Eurasia
which led to the formation of the
Himalayas the Himalayan Mountain Range
so about
so about 100 million years ago India was
still in the middle of the Indian Ocean
about 60 70 million years ago it was
over the reunion hotspot region over
here The Reunion Island
and that's when India uh witnessed the
Deccan region of India witnessed
incredible super volcano activity
the so-called Deccan traps which may
have contributed to the uh demise of our
non-avian dinosaur friends and the the
the impact event in Yucatan Mexico also
contributed to that uh so there were
lots and lots of dinosaur species all
across India and people have been
finding dinosaur eggs and fossils for
decades for for centuries in India but
for some reason Indian scientists have
not shown much interest
paleontologists I don't think
paleontology is even much of a science
in India I was very surprised to know
that we have paleontologists on the
other hand the Chinese
have turned paleontology into a
large-scale industry they've discovered
hundreds of of new species of dinosaurs
in China including very well preserved
fossils including fossils where the
feathers are preserved including fossils
where the feathers are preserved with
proper pigmentation you can see the
color of the feathers you should know
that most dinosaurs had feathers the
great T-Rex most likely also had
feathers and yeah so the Chinese have
taken a huge head start on this and it's
really boosted the tourism because
people want to go to these places uh
these museums and see Chinese dinosaurs
I think India is also going to be home
to incredible numbers of dinosaur
species maybe many species that are
still not known to anyone so I think
it's it's a it's a treasure waiting to
be discovered and I'm not at all
surprised that they found this big
Treasure Trove of dinosaur nests and
fossilized eggs I think this is just the
beginning we're gonna find a huge amount
more of this
says what's the legacy of Egyptian
civilization apart from pyramids mummies
and Pharaohs
what's the legacy of Egypt Beyond
pyramids mummies and Pharaohs
go to Egypt today you won't see any of
the old civilization and culture
anywhere
it has been totally eradicated
so Egypt became part of the it fell to
the Arabian conquests about 1200 1300
maybe 1400 years before today and the
native indigenous culture was
it whatever happened to Iran later also
happened in Egypt uh so the native
culture the native civilization was
totally destroyed eradicated it was
almost impossible to destroy the pyramid
so they still stand
and so on
so nothing of the old
civilization and culture still exists
Beyond those visible symbols of
monumental archeology the Sphinx the the
the pyramids and obviously they are
they're preserving the mummies and all
because it's a great source of income
revenue from tourism egyptology is a big
deal so all that but today is modern
Egyptian culture has nothing to do with
the with the original culture of Egypt
what's the Legacy I think the West kind
of claims Egypt to be one of the sources
of so-called Western Civilization
according to the west Western
Civilization originates in Greece in
Rome in Mesopotamia and Egypt
and obviously among the the the Hebrew
culture so our that's the the that's the
source of Western Civilization according
to people in the west of course that may
or may not be true we don't know I mean
we do know
so that at most is the legacy of
Egyptian civilization that today the
West lays claim to Egypt as one of the
sources
or or fountainheads of Western
Civilization apart from that there's no
other Legacy yes this Monumental
architecture still stands people can go
there and and look at it behold that in
Wonder and awe apart from that nothing
else sad
says in schools if a 50 year old teacher
is not able to teach seven or eight
subjects to kids then why is a 12 year
old forced to learn this seven or eight
subjects which are mostly useless for
them in the future how
I completely agree I have had I mean if
you if you see my ask a budget episodes
I don't know 29 30 30 months around
there I have about three episodes
totally dedicated to education and I've
taken up these issues in that
most of the subjects we are teaching
kids are completely pointless
the only subjects you need to succeed in
life are first of all language which
means communication
one or two languages is enough not five
six seven fifteen languages or three
languages like we have today one
language or two languages at most
firstly you need language communication
communication skills written
communication and verbal communication
and secondly you need mathematics but
not
not algebra trigonometry calculus
differential equations and so on so
tensor calculus matrices no none of that
you only need arithmetic to succeed in
life
you are never going to use calculus or
trigonometry in real life
you're never going to use algebra in
real life
it helps if you know this I mean I love
mathematics I've learned mathematics to
a very high degree very advanced
mathematics but I'm telling you this you
don't need any of that to succeed in
life you only need a very good grasp on
addition subtraction multiplication
division arithmetic mostly that
so you need to know a language or two
languages really well you need to be
good at communicating and you need to be
really good at arithmetic apart from
that it also helps if you know the world
history
and your culture
apart from that you don't need to learn
anything yes some science helps
biology physics not much chemistry
so a little bit of education is needed
but the kind of education we are being
given today is way way way more than
what we need it's it's Overkill it
overburdens children
it makes their lives miserable
so yeah I completely agree with swarup
vaidya and most of these teachers
themselves they can hardly teach one
subject
so yeah we need to change things around
we need to reform the education system
the education system is about
empowering students the stakeholders are
the students not the goddamn teachers
and today who are the stakeholders it's
the teachers
ask yourself a simple question if you
misbehave in class what's going to
happen you may be thrown out of school
now ask yourself this question if a
teacher misbehaves what's this what's
the consequences typically nothing which
means the education system treats the
teachers and the staff as stakeholders
not the students it's a complete
reversal of rules so yeah we need uh
drastic massive major changes in the
education system and nothing of that
sort is happening right now the new
education the new education policy does
not address any of the core issues it is
like applying Band-Aid to a gunshot
wound
Pika says last week I was having my
class 12 bio practical exam I made a
beautiful investigatory project on
genetic similarity between primates and
humans on that day The Examiner was just
seeing the files and throwing them on
the floor
I was so disappointed by this as I
literally spent two weeks for that
project so I wanted to ask you how can
this type of attitude of teachers how
could it be changed and how can this
work of students be valued I I know how
you feel ishika this is typical in the
Indian education system these people
they saw these teachers
examiners are teachers they treat
students as worthless individuals and
you may spend weeks preparing a project
and they'll take a cursory glance at it
and throw it into a pile of trash that's
how it's done they don't value
students they don't value the sentiments
and feelings of students and the work
that students do the work they put in
the problem is the education system it
is because of the education system that
such teachers are are well are are taken
in and they thrive in the system
you know in our culture Indian culture
they say that
that a guru is next to God well please
understand today's teachers are not
gurus there is a world of difference
between a guru and a teacher in the 21st
century today's teachers see a guru
in the old days if you had a guru that
Guru was your Guru for life
and your Guru never asked you for fees
yes you could give a guru dakshina at
the end of the day when you were done
with your education
but your Guru wouldn't would not stop
teaching you if you were for whatever
reason unable to pay money
right today's teachers the moment you
stop paying the fees they will stop
teaching you so today's teachers are not
gurus they are service providers who are
doing work working for you for a fee
that's the difference
um
so the education system needs to be
changed I have spoken about this at
Great length um
I have about three episodes about the
education system I think it's uh around
episode 30 plus or minus one or two
uh so if you want to look into that uh
if you want to know my views about that
you can watch those episodes
um to change this attitude of teachers
first of all teachers who who behave in
this manner should be fired but that's
not possible today because the education
system treats the teachers as
stakeholders not students
so the entire education system needs to
be revamped only then will things change
as far as we are today this is the way
it's gonna keep on going
unfortunate
saurabh says what are your views on the
Takeover of yoga by westerners uh as of
now even Indians don't know the meaning
of uh of yoga for the for Indians it's
just for most people today it's just an
exercise nothing else nothing more even
though yoga is interpreted differently
as per the context of patanjali Rishi
who gave the definition of yoga as yoga
sorry it's too small like
which means
hey
yes so today if you if you go to Google
you know Google image search for yoga
you will see let's let's do it let's do
it
let's go to Google let's let's do it in
real time I've spoken about this before
let's I'm happy to speak about it again
just go to Google and search for yoga
go to images
what do you see
you will see mainly Western people
doing yoga
most of them are people from the West
you will hardly see any Indian doing
yoga at all in all these images it's the
West
it's the Western perception of yoga
and and for the West it's just an
exercise it's all stretching that's what
yoga is so so yoga has been taken over
by the West it is being distorted and
destroyed by the way so I don't I don't
blame them for that for it
the true meaning of yoga has been lost
along the way so the true meaning of
yoga is what you find in the yoga sutras
of patanjali right and and yoga is is
defined as stilling the the waves or the
fluctuations of the mind that's the
definition of yoga the the the
storms that you have in your mind the
unease the the waves the fluctuations
all of that you need to still that that
is the true that is what yoga really is
and yoga in the patanjali sutras has
lots of
branches or limbs you have ethical
principles you have breath control you
have meditation you have concentration
dhyan you have sense withdrawal you have
physical postures and it's all about
ultimate liberation
so
yoga is about
ahinsa non-harming others who don't
deserve any harm it's about truthfulness
it's about discipline it's about not
being greedy it's but it's about not
stealing it's all it's all ethics right
from that perspective it's also about
physical postures So Physical postures
in yoga are described as a means of
preparing the body and the mind for
meditation that's the true
uh purpose of all these physical
postures the asanas right
and for the West it's all stretching
it's all exercise and yoga is also about
breath control pranayama which it's it's
a very important tool it's a fundamental
tool for controlling the mind and for
regulating the energy of the body
meditation begins with breath control so
that's the foundation and you have
sensory withdrawal directing your
indrias your senses in word and avoiding
external sensory distractions where is
that in the western yoga it's also about
dhyana concentration it's a key step for
developing a still mind and a focused
mind focused inwards in into the in into
the internal Universe there are two
universes in external universe and an
internal universe so that's done and the
meditation obviously it's a it's a
process of attaining a higher level of
Consciousness and the goal the ultimate
goal of yoga is the attainment of Moksha
Liberation and the realization of your
true nature is pure Consciousness so
ultimately we have pure Consciousness
that's what yoga says and that is the
goal of yoga Liberation Moksha and
becoming pure Consciousness none of that
is present in what the West does they
are doing uh hot yoga and and dog yoga
and goat yoga and drunk yoga and God
knows what other yoga it is it is
it's it's terrible
and and uh so so the question is what do
you what do we do about this
what do we do about this India needs to
establish a global standards Institute
of your Institute Institute of yoga in
the same way that the Shaolin Temple is
the global standards Institute of kung
fu the same way we have to we need to
have our own Global standards Institute
of yoga and this institute should have
the best people real gurus not fake
gurus with phds phds account for nothing
and
this institute should Define what yoga
is and what yoga is not why are we not
doing it do we lack money do we lack
funds we have the funds
it's not being done it's a sense it's a
lack of leadership you know lack of
caring about Indian culture
yeah so that's disappointing but yeah
that's what I can say about this
all right let's take some um
some of the questions
heart hacker Munda says I am 22 years
old I want a strong physically Fit Body
I also want to lose weight is it good
for young guys like me to do water
fasting or should we not do fasting and
only focus on healthy diet and exercise
it is a good question if you are young
I'm 22 years old right
when you're 22 I would say uh see what's
the purpose of water fasting I have done
water fasting I've done a lot I've I've
done it in a very to an extreme degree
or my longest water fast was 23 days 23
days on only water not a single gram of
food 23 days ridiculous crazy so I did a
23 day water fast I've done a 21 day
water fast I've done a 14 day water fast
I've done a couple of seven day fast
enough a whole bunch of four day water
fast so I am I know this very well how
it works when you do water fasting
especially extended fasting first of all
what's the purpose of water fasting the
real purpose of water fasting is is
detoxification when you give your
digestive system and your liver and
other other organs some rest some
respite
then the body is able to detoxify itself
there are lots of cells in the body that
are that are uh senescent cells damaged
cells so these cells need to be
destroyed otherwise they could cause
cancer 20 years down the line
so when when the body goes in a state of
fasting four days plus then then the
body enters a state of autophagy it uh
recycles all these dead dying deceased
senescent obsolescent cells destroys
them and repurposes the materials that
come out of it for building new cells so
that is detoxification if you have any
precancerous cells they will be
destroyed in that uh so that's the real
purpose of fasting obviously it also uh
removes the need to the thought of food
if you if you can do it and you can
focus more on other work and all that
but the side effect is that it may you
lose a lot of weight you lose weight
very rapidly drastic weight loss and
and it you're gonna become quite weak
physically you're gonna get quite weak
and you're gonna lose weight in mostly
in the form of fat tissue but you will
also lose muscle mass you will lose
muscle mass if you do an extended fast I
know and it's not fun you go to the gym
and work very hard lift heavy weights
for a long time and then you lose that a
significant portion of that in two weeks
that's what happens when you do extended
fasting so if you want to be strong and
physically fit I would say please don't
fast you can do a four day three day
fast that's good for detoxification not
more than that and not very often maybe
once in three months or so it's fine
only for detoxification purposes what
you should do is focus on a healthy diet
and exercise weight training cardio is
good running and all that but weight
training is what you really need that's
going to give you a stronger body and
physically Fit Body and of course that
could also help you lose weight and a
Clean Diet no processed food no junk
food pizzas Burgers all that garbage
pastas eat clean good food lots of
vegetables and whatever protein works
for you so that's what I would say but
so I would say focus on a healthy diet
Clean Diet and regular exercise
hopefully weight training that way you
will have a strong physically Fit Body
and you will also lose weight you will
attain your ideal weight over a course
of several months maybe six months maybe
12 months depending on how overweight
you may be
all right
Mr Jesus says does weight training stunt
your growth your height as a team when
did you start to trade weight training
does not stunt your growth as a team
what weight training does is that it
makes your bones uh denser harder and
stronger obviously you need to have an
adequate intake of of calcium for that
so when you do that when you lift heavy
weights it makes your bones tougher
denser stronger and harder which is good
for you it does not stunt your growth as
a team take the most famous example
Arnold Schwarzenegger the greatest
bodybuilder of all time he started
weight training at the age of 14 or 15
and he went on to be or reasonably tall
man that's six feet plus six one six two
or something
so he's a tall imposing guy he did a lot
of weight training heavyweights when he
went on to be a tall guy uh so yeah it
weight training is good for you it's not
going to stunt your growth as a Dean
when did I start to train well
um I've always been interested in in
weight training in exercise I have the
kind of body that's that likes that
um so I said so when I was a teenager I
did not have access to a gym I used to
crank out hundreds of push-ups in a day
at times at times you know and I was to
improvise make make shift weights and
all that so I've always been interested
in this I was also interested in sport
whenever whenever I got the opportunity
to play that so it's good you need to be
physically active and do go ahead even
if you're a teenager lift weights it's
good for you it will not stunt your
growth at all
and with that I'm going to stop the
questions I'm going to take some
questions from the live chat let's do it
for a few minutes
um
let us see what questions we have okay
in case you have questions you want to
ask in the live chat go ahead and do
that now and I shall take up a few of
these
uh especially the interesting ones
uh
where is it
when you click on something it
disappears om says please tell more
about Oroville is it really the city of
the future I I haven't been there I was
in puducherry last weekend and uh for
the for the G20 uh science initiation
meeting and on the second day we were
all supposed to go to Oroville I skipped
that I do not find it very interesting
for whatever reason I have been to the
aurobindo ashram so Oroville is this
experimental City it's like a communal
place where everybody does some work and
everybody pitches in it's like a
community kind of thing
I am not sure if it's the city of the
future maybe it's a city of the past
and uh yeah so I'm I'm I don't know a
lot about it because I have not visited
it people all do some kind of
handicrafts work or they produce
something at some level
I think uh it's not quite the city of
the future you know people may disagree
this is my own personal personal opinion
if you if you disagree please feel free
to disagree but that's how I think it is
obviously I am not an expert because
I've not been there but I've read about
it and that's what I think
all right uh where what else do we have
Justin Raj Singh with my face on it
okay what's the mystery behind
Rasputin's death Rasputin Grigori
Rasputin was this great Russian Mystic
uh spiritual Guru kind of person who was
the the power behind the crown uh
about a hundred or so years ago he died
uh
he was the the mentor of the Russian
queen or something
and uh there was politically very
powerful he was like the second most
powerful person in the entire Empire and
then he was assassinated by a group of
soldiers Etc maybe the British also had
some hand in it it is believed and they
said that they first tried to poison him
they gave him a stick of cyanide in some
food he ate it nothing happened to him
and then they shot him and then once
again he did not die and he walked away
and then he had to be shot multiple
times and all that he eventually
supposedly died and then they burned the
body and when they were burning the body
it seems the body stood up or something
that's the kind of Legend you hear
so it was also stabbed apparently and
even that did not kill him so yeah it's
the story that one hears that I that I
read as a kid is that he was almost
impossible to kill they tried to poison
him they tried to stab him they shot him
multiple times eventually he died and
when they burned him then the body tried
to stand up or something that's the kind
of story but he has obviously a lot of
it will be embellishments and
exaggerations
but yeah
he was a very powerful man he was
perhaps the power behind the crown at
some point in time in the Russian Empire
all right do we have any other question
that I can take uh
let's see let's see let's see
what do we have
bonium yeah there's a song by Boney M
what Rasputin Rara Rasputin lover of the
Russian Queen
sort of thing yes
let's see what else do we have
57 jet fifth generation fighter can
India by I think India should focus on
developing its own fighter jets we now
have the industrial and technological
capability to build a fourth generation
fighter plane of the Tejas and we are
now building four and four four point
five generation fighter planes which is
the LCA they just Mark II and the
advanced medium combat aircraft and
eventually the deck twin engine deck
based fighter we are also developing a
stealth unmanned stealth aircraft and so
on I think India should focus entirely
on developing its own aircraft stop
buying things we may need to buy
for the time being of your aircraft from
other countries I think the rafale is a
good deal we should not have 500
different kinds of aircraft it's a
nightmare logistical nightmare to
service them all and acquire spare parts
and all that keep it simple
in in the next 20 years India should be
fully reliant on its own aircraft
manufacturing capabilities and I think
in the next 20 years India will be able
to produce a fifth generation fighter
plane maybe even a sixth generation
fighter plane
so that's what I think should happen
uh let's possibly take one more question
do we have anything else
uh
let's see uh lots of questions I can see
Shivan says my opinion about zelinski's
demand to sanction India good good luck
brother zielinski
listen the Americans are in no position
to actually sanction India they need
India on the side the Chinese are
playing wonderful games right now
sending balloons over the US the U.S
still needs a
something to balance China
and they also need something to balance
India so to balance India the Pakistan
and to balance China they are using
India and Japan mainly also Australia to
some extent not really so I don't think
the Americans are in a position to to
accede to zelinski's demand to sanction
India when when you are a guy who works
from home like zielinski and makes
billions of dollars then you have these
these grandiose delusions
so yes it's it's uh
it's it's reasonable it's funny
to see this demand of Mr zielinski to
sanction India okay I think we're going
to end it over here it's already two
hours and seven minutes long our session
so we're gonna end it here thank you so
much for all the questions I hope I have
taken lots of questions today from
different people of course I had many
more that I was supposed to take but as
always one runs out of time
so thank you everybody for the questions
I'm getting thousands of questions every
week and I really appreciate that I'm in
a privileged position that people ask me
thousands of questions every week so
thank you very much to all of you for
your questions for your viewership and I
will see you very soon next week until
then take care thank you